Finding Aid for the Book Artifacts Collection, circa 2345 B.C.-1993 A.D. (bulk circa 1510-1976)
The Bancroft Library
Book Artifacts Collection
circa 2345 B.C.-1993 A.D.
circa 1510-1976
BART 1
ca. 1360 items (4 selected digital objects)
The Bancroft Library. University of California, Berkeley Berkeley, CA 94720-6000 Phone: (510) 642-6481 Fax: (510) 642-7589 Email: bancref@library.berkeley.edu URL: http://bancroft.berkeley.edu/
The Book Artifacts Collection contains material relating to the development of writing, the history of printing, and the book arts (circa 2345 B.C.-1993 A.D.). This collection of artifacts and other realia illustrates various aspects of book production and design, from early cuneiform clay tablets, papyri, seals, and other writing materials, book curiosities and miniature books to the 20th century book, including printing presses and later 20th century printing devices. The bulk of the collection deals with hand and machine printing and binding. The collection includes specimens of various types of binding, binder's tools and equipment; illustration, relief, photographic and photomechanical processes; paper-making; practical pressroom and composing room equipment and presses; type design, type founding, and type-setting; music engraving; cartography; and specialty printing.
Information for Researchers
Collection is open for research.
BART 1 A5087 is located in the Center for Tebtunis Papyri (O.Berkeley 1).
BART 1 A5088 is located in the Center for Tebtunis Papyri (No. 1-30 in O.Tebt (3, 5, 14, 16, and 18 are recorded as missing)).
BART 1 A5P27 is unaccessioned currently but held by the Center for Tebtunis Papyri.
BART 1 A5S86, No. 2 is located in the Center for Tebtunis Papyri (labeled Egyptian Stone Writing).
BART 1 A5W66 is located in the Center for Tebtunis Papyri (T.Tebt. 1).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog
Binding finishing hardware; Bookbinding equipment; Computers; Cutting tools; Electrotypes (printing plates/blocks); Flong; Galleys (type composition equipment); Imposition (Printing); Matrices (copper molds); Miniature books (Publishing); Molds (papermaking); Movable type; Octavo format (Printing); Papermaking tools and equipment; Papyri; Photoengravings (prints); Printers' devices (Printing); Printing press components; Printing presses; Proofs (Printing); Quarto format (Printing); Seals (artifacts); Stereotypes (printing plates/blocks); Tablets; Type specimens; Typewriters; Wood blocks (printing blocks)
Administrative Information
Items from various sources, including gifts to the library.
The Book Artifacts Collection contains material relating to the development of writing, the history of printing, and the book arts (circa 2345 B.C.-1993 A.D.). This collection of artifacts and other realia illustrates various aspects of book production and design, from early cuneiform clay tablets, papyri, seals, and other writing materials, to book curiosities, miniature books, and the 20th century book, including printing presses and later 20th century printing devices. The bulk of the collection consists of hand and machine printing and binding. The collection includes specimens of various types of binding, binder's tools and equipment; illustration, relief, photographic and photomechanical processes; paper-making; practical pressroom and composing room equipment and presses; type design, type founding, and type-setting; music engraving; cartography; and specialty printing.
The collection comprises materials that have come from a variety of sources, mostly through gifts and donations. Leslie Clark, who was in charge of rare books and book artifacts until her death in 1979, devised the original classification scheme, which is composed of nineteen series that are alphanumerically ordered from A5 to Z(0-6). The Guide to the Book Artifacts Collection (Flora Elizabeth Reynolds, 2nd, 1999) (the “Guide”) provides an overview of the collection at a series level and cursory overview at the item level. The series level descriptions from the Guide are included in this finding aid. The Register for the Book Artifacts Collection (the “Register”) is composed of four volumes and provides a complete description of the collection at an item level and detailed subject and name index for the collection circa 1986; the Guide includes additional updates to the collection between 1986-1999. This finding aid references both the Register and the Guide to provide for the most comprehensive and consistent series, sub-series and item level descriptions of the artifacts in the collection. The Register has been transcribed into this finding aid to the extent that it could be copied. Therefore, pages that include decorations or hand-written notes were not transcribed. However, the Register has been digitized and is available in four searchable PDF documents (one PDF document per volume) with this finding aid.
The majority of this collection consists of artifacts that relate to the processes of hand and machine printing and binding. Series B5 and Series B6 include materials relating to case, or commercial bookbinding and the hand binding of books, respectively. Series B6 is a large collection that includes sewing supplies, nipping presses, finishing tools, and illustrations of the hand binding process. Series D4 is the Cheri Archive, which includes Peter Koch’s records and working papers for the production of an English translation of Colette’s novel Cheri. Series F6, Format, Imposition, Register and Folding, includes a series of imposition examples, which represent the important pre-press process of arranging the printed book’s pages on a printer’s sheet to allow for faster printing and easier binding. Series I4 and I5, Design, Decoration, and Illustration, contain artifacts and examples of design, decoration and illustration in books. Series I4, Hand Illumination, includes an example of hand illumination. Series I5, Intaglio and Relief Processes, consists of woodblocks, woodcuts, wood engravings, etching and linocuts. Series I52, Electrotyping and Stereotyping, includes electrotyping and stereotyping plates for the reproduction of illustrations and other printed matter. Series I53, Photographic Processes, consists of halftone photoengravings and lithography. Series I54, Photochemical Processes, relates to photochemical processes such as photopolymer printing. Series I55, Prints, Proofs and Drawings, includes examples of various printing processes such as woodblocks, woodcuts, wood engravings, and photoengravings. Series P2, Papermaking and Trade, Handmade Paper and Machine-Made Paper, includes equipment for papermaking and samples of hand-made and machine-made paper. Series P7, Practical Printing, Pressroom and Composing Equipment, contains printing tools, types and equipment. Many of these items are in the Press Room of The Bancroft Library and are used for demonstrations on the principles of hand printing. Series T8, Typography, consists of specimens of movable type, matrices, punches and counterpunches. Subseries T86, Casting and setting by machine, includes displays that illustrate the principles of casting type by machine, a collection of typecast ornaments from the Merrymount Press and John Henry Nash, assembled matrices and examples of forms on monotype and linotype machines, and, finally, examples of stereotyping plates.
The remaining portion of the collection consists of the following Series: Alphabets, Writing Materials, and Writings in Various Forms (Series A5); Music Engraving (Series V2); Map printing (Series V3); Specialty printing (Series W2); and Supplementary Collections (Series Z). Series A5 includes hieroglyphic inscriptions on a fragment of limestone (ca. 2345-2330 B.C.), Sumerian Cuneiform writing on clay tablets from the third millennium B.C., examples of alphabets and letterforms, pens, and book curiosities such as miniature and microscopic books. The music engraving collection, Series V2, belonged to one of the last music engravers in the United States, Richard B. Pettit. Series W2 includes specialty printing from the Panama-Pacific International Exposition. Series Z includes historical artifacts, the Beulah Mitchell Clute Collection, seals, book arts medals, materials relating to the printing the guide, and commemorative postage stamps.
The Guide of the Book Artifacts Collection, by Flora Elizabeth Reynolds is located in the Main (Gardner) Stacks and in The Bancroft Library Reference Collection under the call number Z116.A3 R49 1999. The Register and Index to the BART Collection is located in The Bancroft Library reference desk under the call number E13.B23 R44 1986.
Container Listing
- The book: artifacts related to the development of writing and the production of books: register and index., 1986; E13.B23 R44 1986; 4 volumes
  - The book: artifacts related to the development of writing and the production of books: register and index (Volume 1), 1986; Flora Elizabeth Reynolds; Bancroft Library; E13.B23 R44 1986 v. 1; 388 pages
    Indexing Terms
    Book design -- Library resources; Graphic arts -- Library resources; Printing -- Library resources; Writing -- Library resources
  - The book: artifacts related to the development of writing and the production of books: register and index (Volume 2), 1986; Flora Elizabeth Reynolds; Bancroft Library; E13.B23 R44 1986 v. 2; 336 pages
  - The book: artifacts related to the development of writing and the production of books: register and index (Volume 3), 1986; Flora Elizabeth Reynolds; Bancroft Library; E13.B23 R44 1986 v. 3; 204 pages
  - The book: artifacts related to the development of writing and the production of books: register and index (Volume 4), 1986; Flora Elizabeth Reynolds; Bancroft Library; E13.B23 R44 1986 v. 4; 267 pages
- Alphabets, Writing Materials, and Writings in Various Forms, A5
  Internal Classification System
  One of the most striking examples of ancient writing in The Bancroft Library is a hieroglyphic inscription (ca. 2345-2330 B.C.) that includes the cartouche of the Pharaoh Teti and part of an offering-list of clothes and oils. The inscription is in sunken relief on a fragment of limestone, probably from a false door in the tomb of a court official at Saqqara. Over the centuries Egyptian hieroglyphics changed greatly, eventually becoming conventionalized in the demotic script shown on the ostracon, or pottery fragment, of the 1st century B.C. It contains a list of the work-days of a man and oxen and a report of food and compensation for the oxen.
  Cuneiform, or wedge-shaped, writing of the third millennium B.C. appears on three clay tablets from Sumer: one, given in memory of Regent Theodore R. Meyer, has been described in Bancroftiana, No. 59 (Oct. 1974); another given by Dr. and Mrs. John Barr Tompkins, records a consignment of wine, bread, and oil in the city of Nippur; and a third, notes the issue of bread and beer to an individual in the city of Umma. A fourth tablet, also in Sumerian characters, belongs to the second millennium B.C. and celebrates the building of the palace of King Sin-Kashid, “The Mighty Governor-King of Uruk.” The last two tablets as well as the limestone fragment and the ostracon described earlier are the gift of Charlotte and Norman H. Strouse.
  The runic alphabet used among the Germanic peoples of the Christian era is represented by a facsimile of the 10th century stone on which the Danish King Harold Bluetooth honored his father and mother. Nearer our own time are a 19th century parchment phylactery fragment and an early 20th century Chinese chop, the latter probably a date stamp used in a business office.
  Distinguished English letterforms may be seen on a facsimile, prepared by Adrian Wilson, of the slate on which John Baskerville, 18th century “writing master,” offers “to cut grave stones in any hand” (original in Birmingham, England). And a printing plate handcut in relief by August Rosenberger reproduces an alphabet of rustic capitals designed by the modern calligrapher and type designer Hermann Zapf.
  Pens include a goose quill of the kind used during the American Revolution, several 19th century pens, the gold pen with which President Taft signed the Congressional resolution permitting him to invite foreign countries to participate in the Panama-Pacific International Exposition, and the wooden pen President Coolidge used to sign the Boulder Dam authorization.
  Among book curiosities are a few examples of miniature and microscopic books, chiefly religious texts.
  - Alphabets: Letterforms, A5A57
    - Baskerville slate (facsimile), A5A57, No. 1
    - Hermann Zapf plate: alphabet in rustic capitals, A5A57, No. 2
  - Cuneiform Writing on Clay, A5C53
    - Sumerian [ca. 2028 B.C.], A5C53, No. 1
    - Sumerian [ca. 2300-2100 B.C.], A5C53, No. 2
    - Sumerian [ca. 2033 B.C.], A5C53, No. 3
    - Sumerian [ca. 1860-1830 B.C.], A5C53, No. 4
    - Sumerian [ca. 2038-2030 B.C.], A5C53, No. 5
  - Ink, A5I35
    - Iron gall ink (modern recreation), A5I35, No. 1
  - Book Curiosities: Microscopic and Miniature Books, A5M53
  - Ostracon, A5087
    - Demotic hierogylphic [Egyptian] inscription [75-100 B.C.], A5087, No. 1
  - Ostraca, A5088
    - Varied Pieces, A5088, No. 1-26
  - Papyrus, A5P27
    - Fragments (for students to touch), A5P27, No. 1
    - Modern examples, A5P27, No. 2-3
  - Parchment, A5P28
    - Phylactery fragment, A5P28, No. 1
    - Sample, A5P28, No. 2
  - Pens, A5P36
    - Goose quill, A5P36, No. 1
    - Pen-holder and pen: red wood and steel-plated brass [188?], A5P36, No. 2
    - Pen-holder and pen: mother-of-pearl inlay, A5P36, No. 3
    - President Coolidge Boulder Dam pen, A5P36, No. 4
  - Seals, A5S39
    See also BART Z2 and BART Z3
    - Chinese [1910], A5S39, No. 1
  - Stone, A5S86
    - Rune stone: Harald Bluetooth, ca. 950 A.D. (facsimile), A5S86, No. 1
    - Limestone fragment: [Egyptian] hieroglyphic inscription [ca. 2345-2330 B.C.], A5S86, No. 2
  - Vellum, A5V35
    - Samples, A5V35, No. 1-3
  - Wax, A5W28
    - Roman tablet (facsimile), A5W28, No. 1
  - Wood, A5W66
    - Mummy docket [ca. 200 B.C.-200 A.D.], A5W66, No. 1
- Bookbinding Equipment: Case Binding, B5
  The bookbinding collection in two main divisions: B5, Case, or Commercial, Binding: and B6, Hand Binding. Case binding procedures are shown in bookbinders’ dummies, paste-ups, press proof, and several bindings in progressive states of manufacture. Finished cases typify ornate 19th century commercial styles.
  - [Case binding (miscellaneous)], B5C2
    - Cased book in component parts, B5C2, No. 1
    - Case binding with unsewn signatures, B5C2, No. 2
    - Cased book partially dissected to show details of construction, B5C2, No. 3
    - Book in parts, with illustrations tipped-in, B5C2, No. 4
    - Advance sheets folded and collated for publisher's approval, B5C2, No. 5
    - Unbound signatures with prospectus, B5C2, No. 6
    - Book ready for case, B5C2, No. 7
    - Unbound signatures: Cowan's Bibliography of California, B5C2, No. 8
    - Unbound signature: Grabhorn King Lear, B5C2, No. 9
  - Cases: specimens, B5C3
    - Embroidered, B5C3, No. 1
    - Wood: carved, B5C3, No. 2
    - Calf: tooled, B5C3, No. 3
    - Cloth, B5C3, No. 4
    - Calf: tooled, B5C3, No. 5
    - Pigskin: Byzantine style, B5C3, No. 6
    - Pigskin: blind stamp, B5C3, No. 7
    - Calf: Mottled, B5C3, No. 8
  - Bookbinders' dummies, B5D8
    - Oregon Historical Society, Portland, B5D8, No. 1
    - Cross, Ralph Herbert, B5D8, No. 2
    - Shirk, David Lawson, B5D8, No. 3
  - Cloth binding: title-label pasteup and press proof, B5E2
    - Godfrey, Edward Settle, B5E2, No. 1
  - Electrotypes, Bookbinder's, B5E5
    - Tommasini, Amadee R., B5E5, No. 1
    - Merrymount Press Collection, B5E5 M38
  - [Bookbinding equipment miscellaneous], B5E6
    - Brass Die, B5E6, No. 1
    - Merrymount Press Collection, B5E6 M38
- Bookbinding Equipment: Hand Binding, B6
  The second division of the Bookbinding Equipment collection is Hand Binding (B6). The handing binding collection, far larger and more complex than the Case Binding collection (B5), would supply a very complete shop. Much of it came to the University from the Blake House, now the President’s residence, formerly the home of Anita D. S. Blake (Mrs. Anson Blake), an amateur binder. There are all kinds of sewing supplies, a sewing stick, a sewing frame, and an array of such necessities as backing boards, hammers, pressing tins, weights, stoves, glue pots, paring knives, skiving blades, polishing irons, and burnishing tools. One of the nipping presses belonged to Frederick Folger Thomas, Jr.; the other Valenti Angelo constructed for his own use. The lying press, with two handmade ploughs, and the tall standing press were made in France, as were many of the tools. For finishing, or decorating book covers, brass fillets, pallets, tools, and stamps, mounted in handles, offer curves, lines, hearts, stars, circles, and fleurs-de-lys, virtually limitless in design possibilities. Sets of alphabets and numerals, also mounted in handles, and a bookbinder’s cabinet of binder’s type afford a choice of letterform styles for titles.
  Examples of materials include modern pulp-board, marbled paper swatches, booklets of cloth and cover-board samples, a series of carefully labeled leather samples, the last assembled and given by Stephen Gale Herrick.
  The whole process of hand binding is illustrated in a series of laminated panels prepared by the distinguished binder Stella Patri for exhibition at the Golden Gate International Exposition in San Francisco in 1939.
  - [Display of Hand Binding Process by Stella Patri], B6A5
    - Display Set: Stella Patri, B6A5, No. 1-16
  - Gluing Equipment, B6B24
    - Double iron glue pot, B6B24, No. 1
    - Glue, B6B24, No. 2
  - Patterns and examples of trial tooling, B6D3
    - Patterns, B6D3, No. 1
    - Patterns, B6D3, No. 2
    - Trial tooling with black morocco, B6D3, No. 3
    - Trial tooling on brown calf, B6D3, No. 4
    - Trial tooling on blue morocco, B6D3, No. 5
    - Trial tooling on blue morocco, B6D3, No. 6
  - Forwarding and finishing equipment, B6F5
    - Burnishing tools, B6F51, No. 1-3
    - Gilding Material, B6F512
    - Gilding Boards, B6F513, No. 1-3
    - Letterforms (alphabets) mounted in handles, B6F52, No. 1-8
    - Gouges (curved lines) mounted in handles, B6F54, No. 1-5
    - Line pallets mounted in handles, B6F55, No. 1-4
    - Numerals and punctuation marks mounted in handles, B6F56, No. 1-8
    - Ornaments mounted in handles, B6F57, No. 1-8
    - Merrymount Press, B6F575, M1-M24
    - Fillets (rolls) mounted in handles, B6F58, No. 1-5
    - Fillets (rolls) with special designs mounted in handles, B6F582, No. 1-5
    - Handles, B6F59, No. 1-37
    - Edging knives, B6F61, No. 1-3
    - Paring knives, B6F612, No. 1-3
    - Pointes, B6F613, No. 1-3
    - Skiving blade mounted in Stanley holder, B5F614, No. 1
    - Polishing irons, B6F62, No. 1-2
    - Finishing boards, B6F64, No. 1-2
    - Gas tooling stoves, B6F65, No. 1-3
    - Polishing sheets, B6F67, No. 1-9
    - Backing boards, B6F71, No. 1
    - Hammers, B6F73, No. 1-2
    - Binder's types in binder's cabinet, B6F85
    - Lettering pallets, B6F853, No. 1-6
    - Transfer materials, B6F854, No. 1-3
  - Paring stones, B6L5
    - Lithograph stone, B6L5, No. 1
    - Lithograph stone, B6L5, No. 2
    - Granite stone: rectangular, with bale handle, B6L5, No. 3
  - Binder's materials, B6M3
    - 19th C. materials, B6M32, No. 1-4
    - Leather samples, B6M33, No. 1-22
    - Cover board samples, B6M34, No. 1
    - Cloth sample books and price lists, B6M35, No. 1-5
    - Mull (muslim) samples, B6M355
    - Metal accesories: bosses, clasps, nails and brads, B6M36, No. 1-5
    - Paper samples, B6M37, No. 1-7
    - Marbled paper samples, B6M372, No. 1-5
    - Dealers' sample booklets, marbled and decorated papers, B6M374, No. 1-8
  - Binder's presses, B6P7
    - Standing Press, French, B6P7, No. 1
    - Nipping Press, B6P7, No. 2
    - Lying Press, French, B6P7, No. 3
    - Nipping press (small, homemade standing press), B6P7, No. 4
    - Pressing boards, B6P71, No. 1-16
    - Ploughs and blades, B6P72, No. 1-3
    - Extra Blades, B6P721, No. 1-2
    - Cutting boards, B6P73, No. 1-6
    - Pressing tins, B6P74, No. 1-6
    - Trindles, B6P77, No. 1-3
    - Weights, B6P78, No. 1-10
  - [Miscellaneous sewing equipment], B6S3
    - Sewing frame, B6S3, No. 1
    - Sewing supplies: threads, cords, tapes, and needles, B6S35
    - Sewing stick, B6S38
  - General equipment, tools and supplies, B6T7
    - Mixing tray, B6T7, No. 1
    - Cup: metal, B6T7, No. 2
    - File: metal, B6T7, No. 3
    - Metal polish, B6T7, No. 4
    - Almond Oil, B6T7, No. 5
    - Coconut Oil, B6T7, No. 6
    - Gum arabic, B6T7, No. 7
    - Punches, B6T7, No. 8
    - Dye: red, B6T7, No. 9
    - Straight edge: metal, B6T7, No. 10
    - T-square: metal, B6T7, No. 11
- Design and Production of Books, D4
  The Cheri archive contains Peter Koch’s records and working papers for the production of Janet Flanner’s English translation of Colette’s novel Cheri (San Francisco, George F. Ritchie, 1983). They comprise estimates of the number of lines, pages, and forms for printing; calculations of the paper supply needed; trial layouts and design proofs; printing procedures; binding possibilities; and notes of costs and payments.
  - Peter Koch: Cheri archive, D4K6
    - Introductory papers, D4K6, No. 1
    - Character count, D4K6, No. 2
    - Selecting paper and figuring quantity, D4K6, No. 3
    - Title-page design, D4K6, No. 4
    - Title design proofs, D4K6, No. 5
    - Page design, D4K6, No. 6
    - Printing procedures, D4K6, No. 7
    - Binding, D4K6, No. 8
    - Spine label, D4K6, No. 9
    - Brochure, D4K6, No. 10
    - Costs, D4K6, No. 11
- Format, Imposition, Register and Folding, F6
  The major part of this section is a series of imposition examples, printed sheets and blank sheets, numbered to correspond to the illustrations (pp. 88-105) in Philip Gaskell's New Introduction to Bibliography (Oxford: Claredon Press, 1972).
  - Imposition examples: printed sheets, F67 G46-60
    "G" numbers refer also to illustrations [pp. 88-105] in Gaskell, Phillip. New Introductions to Bibliography. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1972 (Ref. Z1001 G2)
    - Early 19th C. printed sheet, F67, No. 1
    - Folio: outer and inner forms in sixes, F67 G46
    - Quarto: outer form, F67 G47, No. 1
    - Quarto: outer form, F67 G47, No. 2
    - Quarto: outer and inner forms with three varients. Unbound book: Pallsay, Bernard. A Delectable Garden, F67 G47, No. 3
    - Quarto: outer and inner forms of two half-sheets worked together, F67 G48
    - Quarto: outer and inner forms imposed for work-and-turn, F67 G49
    - Octavo: outer and inner forms, F67 G50, No. 1
    - Octavo: outer and inner forms with tipped-on end sheets, F67 G50, No. 2
    - Octavo: outer form, F67 G50, No. 3
    - Octavo: outer and inner forms, except last gathering, which has folio tipped-on end sheet. Dishbound book: Ruiz, Juan. The Book of Good Love, F67 G50, No. 4
    - Sextodecimo: outer and inner forms of two half-sheets worked together before cutting, F67 G60
  - Imposition examples: blank sheets, F672, G1-G60
    - Broadside. Discussed in Gaskell, p. 81. [Not illustrated in Gaskell], F672 G1
    - Folio, F672 G46, No. 1
    - Folio: three sheets of folio quired in sixes, F672 G46, No. 2
    - Quarto, F672 G47, No. 1
    - Quarto, quired. Discussed in Gaskell, p. 82, F672 G47, No. 2
    - Octavo, common., F672 G50, No. 1
    - Octavo, common., F672 G50 No. 2
    - Octavo, quired. Discussed in Gaskell, p. 82, F672 G50, No. 3
    - Octavo with cancels. Discussed in Gaskell, p. 134-135, 351, F672 G50, No. 4
    - Long duedecimo, folded, F672 G54
    - Duedecimo, common, cut., F672 G55, No. 1